Guide to the Halton Cheadle Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Halton Cheadle collection
1982-1987
MS 1595
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
The collection consists of legal papers and other materials from the firm of Cheadle, Thompson & Haysom of Port Elizabeth, South Africa. The firm represented Dr. Wendy Orr and forty-two other applicants in obtaining an interim restraining order against the South African police in September 1985. Included are affidavits of the applicants and printed matter relating to instances of excessive police force, legal challenges to the state of emergency measures, legal aspects of apartheid, and groups protesting detention policies in South Africa.
Cheadle, Halton, 1949-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Halton Cheadle, 1988.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of legal papers and other materials from the firm of Cheadle, Thompson & Haysom of Port Elizabeth, South Africa. The firm represented Dr. Wendy Orr and forty-two other applicants in obtaining an interim restraining order from the Port Elizabeth Supreme Court against the South African police in September 1985. Dr. Orr, as district surgeon, charged that detainees held under the country's state of emergency decree in Port Elizabeth and Uitenhage were brutally assaulted on a massive scale by the police.
The bulk of the collection consists of the affidavits of the applicants. Supplementary material includes printed matter pertaining to other instances of excessive police force, legal challenges to the state of emergency measures, legal aspects of apartheid, and groups protesting detention policies in South Africa.
Detention of persons -- South Africa; Police -- South Africa -- Complaints against; Political prisoners -- South Africa; Trials -- South Africa; South Africa -- Trials, litigation, etc.; Cheadle, Halton, 1949-
- Photocopy of a case filed in the Supreme Court of South Africa (South-Eastern Cape Local Division) in the matter between Wendy Pauline Orr and 42 others
  - Pages 1-872, 1985 September (Box 1, Folder 1 - 4)
  - Pages 873-1246 (pages 990-1002 are missing), 1985 September (Box 2, Folder 5 - 7)
- Wendy Orr case newspaper clippings, 1985 September-Dec, 1986 January (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Neil Aggett inquest affidavits, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Seminar on Legal Aspects of Apartheid: The Inquest into the Death in Detention of Isaac Tshifhiwa Moufhe, 1985 July 6-7 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Uitenhage/Langa township shootings: newspaper clippings, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Post-mortem reports on Sparrow Mkhonto, Fort Calata, Siselo Mhlawuli, and Matthew Goniwe, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Police brutality depositions from Graaff-Reinet and other locations, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Printed material on Goniwe, Calata, Mkhonto, and Mhlawuli, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Printed material on detention and torture in South Africa, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- "Memorandum on the Suffering of Children in South Africa," published by Black Sash, 1986 April (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Metal and Allied Workers Union (South Africa) vs. The State President: case and newspaper clippings, 1986 June (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Archbishop G. F. Daniel et. al. vs. Ministers of Law and Order: case and newspaper clippings, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Bophuthatswana/Wintervald shooting: newspaper clippings, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- "Communist Influence in South Africa," [U.S. State Department summary], 1987 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Detainees' Parents Support Committee: reports and printed material, 1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
- "Abantwana Bazabalaza: A Memorandum on Children Under Repression in South Africa," published by Detainees' Parents Support Committee [missing pages 204-211], undated (Box 2, Folder 22)